{"tossups": [{"question": "Wesley Osmus was drowned by the losing side in this battle. Victory in this battle was made possible by the cracking of the JN-25 code, completed with a ruse regarding water purification systems. William Halsey\u2019s illness forced Raymond Spruance to take command during this battle, in which four Japanese aircraft carriers were sunk. For ten points, name this 1942 battle near a namesake atoll, often identified as a turning point in the Pacific theater.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Midway</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this film, Brad Kane and Lea Salonga sing a duet that won an Oscar for Best Original Song. After marketing disputes, Dan Castellaneta replaced one voice actor in this film\u2019s first sequel. Thirty percent of respondents to a December 2015 PPP poll supported bombing Agrabah, this movie\u2019s setting, where Jafar seeks a magic lamp. Robin Williams voiced the Genie in, for ten points, what 1992 Disney film adapted from<em> The Arabian Nights</em>?", "answer": "<b> Aladdin</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This river is crossed by the John Frost Bridge, which replaced a structure fought over in the Battle of Arnhem during Operation Market Garden. For many years, the Roman Empire\u2019s Germanic frontier began at the Danube and this river, which also forms Liechtenstein\u2019s western border. For ten points, name this longest river entirely within Western Europe, which flows from the Alps through Germany to the North Sea.", "answer": "<b> Rhine</b> River (or<b> Rijn</b> River)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The world\u2019s first openly lesbian prime minister was elected in this country, which saw the Kitchenware Revolution after all three of its largest banks collapsed in the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis. This nation\u2019s Althing is the world\u2019s oldest existing parliamentary institution. Massive air travel disruptions across Europe resulted from the 2010 eruption of the Eyjafjallajokull [EYE-a-fyat-la-yo-kutl] volcano in this country. For ten points, name this Scandinavian island nation whose capital is Reykjavik.", "answer": "<b> Iceland</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This dynasty\u2019s power was interrupted by Wu Zetian\u2019s brief Second Zhou Dynasty and by the An Lushan rebellion. Emperor Gaozu founded, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty that preceded the Song Dynasty?", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name these shantytowns formed during the Great Depression, which were named for the predecessor to Franklin Roosevelt.", "answer": "<b> Hooverville</b>s (prompt on descriptions of slums, shantytowns, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One philosopher born in this nation was the lover of Alexander Berkman, the attempted assassin of Henry Clay Frick. The pamphlet \u201cWhat Is To Be Done\u201d supported the establishment of a \u201cvanguard\u201dto ferment revolution in this country. That pamphlet was written by an author from this country who traveled from Switzerland in a sealed boxcar and delivered the April Theses upon his return to Petrograd. For ten points, name this home country of Emma Goldman and Vladimir Lenin.", "answer": "<b> Russia</b> (accept<b> USSR</b> or<b> Soviet Union</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man left his job after his employer was seduced by 80 dancing girls. This philosopher argued that words must be made to fit reality through a process of \u201crectification of names,\u201d and his Five Relationships included ones between father and son and brother to brother. This man, who served under the Prince of Lu, believed in cultivating a trait known as \u201cren\u201d. For ten points, name this Chinese philosopher, the author of the<em> Analects</em>.", "answer": "<b> Confucius</b> (accept<b> Kong Zi</b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "Three brothers and a sister legendarily founded this city by two mountains and a river, and Hilarion was proclaimed as this city\u2019s Metropolitan by one of its rulers, nicknamed \u201cthe Wise\u201d. Nestor chronicled the history of this city in his Primary Chronicle, and this city was founded at the intersection of the Desna and the Dnieper Rivers. A Rurikid line that ruled this city was started by Vladimir the Great, whose son, Yaroslav the Wise, continued this city\u2019s tradition of Christianity. For ten points, name this city, the medieval home of the Rus people and the modern capital of Ukraine.", "answer": "<b> Kiev</b> (accept<b> Kievan Rus</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man vowed to never travel by train again after suffering an injured leg in the Hightstown rail accident with John Quincy Adams. Gideon Welles initially refused this man\u2019s donation of his largest personal steamship to the Union Fleet, and this owner of the Staten Island Ferry feuded with James Fisk and Jay Gould over his railroad empire. For ten points, name this 19th century American, known as \u201cCommodore\u201d for his extensive transportation empire, whose philanthropy founded a university in Tennessee.", "answer": "Cornelius<b> Vanderbilt</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>An 1883 Convention for the protection of intellectual property was signed in this city and is still in effect. The Confederation of the Rhine was initially convened in this city.</b> <b>A series of post-World War I treaties reinforcing the (+)</b> <b>boundaries of defeated nations</b> <b>including the Treaties of Sevres, Trianon, and (*)</b> Neuilly-sur-Seine were signed in this city, which was also the site of treaties ending the Spanish-American War and the Revolutionary War. For ten points, name this city, the namesake of many treaties and the capital of France.", "answer": "<b> Paris</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One side moored their ships at the Dog\u2019s Tail during this battle, and the eventual victors</b> <b>entrenched near a grove sacred to Heracles. The city of (+)</b> <b>entrenched near a grove sacred to Heracles. The city of (+)</b> <b>Eretria had been sacked prior</b> <b>Eretria had been sacked prior</b> <b>to this battle, where the victors were joined by a small force of Plataeans.</b> <b>to this battle, where the victors were joined by a small force of Plataeans.</b> <b>to this battle, where the victors were joined by a small force of Plataeans.</b> <b>The Carneia</b> <b>prevented the arrival of a (*)</b> Spartan army to this battle, where the victors accidentally used a Spartan army to this battle, where the victors accidentally used a Spartan army to this battle, where the victors accidentally used a double envelopment after thinning out their center to defeat Datis and Artaphernes. Miltiades defeated the invasion of Darius I in, for ten points, what battle, after which Pheideppides ran 26 miles to bring news of victory over the Persians to Athens.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Marathon</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a political cartoon, one of these organizations is told, \u201cby the Great Eternal, I\u2019ll cleave thee to the earth!\u201d by a man wielding a cane labeled \u201cVeto.\u201d State, rather than federal, charters established the (+) \u201cwildcat\u201d type of these institutions, some of which were called\u201cpets,\u201d as they were given excess federal (*)</b> money. Until Andrew Jackson\u2019s intervention, Nicholas Biddle led, for ten points, what type of financial institution that, in the 19th century, issued their own currency?", "answer": "<b> bank</b>s (accept the<b> Second Bank of the United States</b>)  (1) <b>This ruler won at the Battles of Terek River and Kondurcha River over</b> <b>Tokhtamysh\u2019s Golden Horde. He later captured Bayezid I in the Battle of Ankara and</b> <b>legendarily built a (+) pyramid of skulls after sacking Delhi. This man, who died en</b> <b>route to invading the Ming Dynasty, established his empire\u2019s capital at (*)</b> Samarkand. For ten points, name this Central Asian ruler who tried to revive the Mongol Empire. ANSWER:<b> Tamerlane</b> or<b> Timur the Lame</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}